export default {
  notes: [
    {
      heading: "Introduction",
      content: "Electric charge is a fundamental property of matter..."
    }
  ],
  mcqs: [
    {
      question: "SI unit of charge is?",
      options: ["Coulomb", "Ampere", "Volt", "Ohm"],
      answer: 0
    }
  ],
  pyqs: [



{
  question: "Isolation of DNA from a fungal cell can be achieved by using:",
  options: [
    "(A) Cellulase",
    "(B) Chitinase",
    "(C) Lysozyme",
    "(D) Protease"
  ],
  answer: "(B) Chitinase"
},

{
  question: "Identify the incorrect statement regarding PCR.",
  options: [
    "(A) Annealing is required to separate both the strands of template DNA.",
    "(B) Two sets of primers are required during polymerisation.",
    "(C) The process of replication is repeated multiple times to produce one billion copies.",
    "(D) Thermostable DNA polymerase is used for extension of primers."
  ],
  answer: "(A) Annealing is required to separate both the strands of template DNA."
},

{
  question: "Amplification of gene of interest by using DNA polymerase may go upto:",
  options: [
    "(A) 1 million times",
    "(B) 1 trillion times",
    "(C) 0.1 million times",
    "(D) 1 billion times"
  ],
  answer: "(D) 1 billion times"
},

{
  question: "The cloning site present in the tetracycline resistance gene of E.coli cloning vector pBR322 is:",
  options: [
    "(A) Pst I",
    "(B) Pvu II",
    "(C) EcoR I",
    "(D) Sal I"
  ],
  answer: "(A) Pst I"
},

{
  question: "Select the correct statement from the following biotechnological procedures:",
  options: [
    "(A) Gel electrophoresis is used for amplification of a DNA segment.",
    "(B) PCR is used for isolation and separation of gene of interest.",
    "(C) Plasmid DNA acts as vector to transfer the piece of DNA attached to it.",
    "(D) The polymerase enzyme joins the gene of interest and the vector DNA."
  ],
  answer: "(C) Plasmid DNA acts as vector to transfer the piece of DNA attached to it."
},

{
  question: "Which native plasmid did Stanley Cohen and Herbert Boyer use for the construction of the first recombinant DNA?",
  options: [
    "(A) Haemophilus influenzae",
    "(B) Salmonella typhimurium",
    "(C) Escherichia coli",
    "(D) Streptococcus pneumoniae"
  ],
  answer: "(C) Escherichia coli"
},

{
  question: "Restriction Endonuclease Hind II cuts DNA by recognising a specific sequence of:",
  options: [
    "(A) Three base pairs",
    "(B) Seven base pairs",
    "(C) Four base pairs",
    "(D) Six base pairs"
  ],
  answer: "(D) Six base pairs"
},

{
  question: "Which statement is correct for observing DNA separation by agarose gel electrophoresis?",
  options: [
    "(A) Ethidium bromide stained DNA can be seen under UV light.",
    "(B) DNA can be seen without staining in visible light.",
    "(C) Ethidium bromide stained DNA can be seen in visible light.",
    "(D) DNA can be seen in visible light."
  ],
  answer: "(A) Ethidium bromide stained DNA can be seen under UV light."
},

{
  question: "Which one of the following is not a feature of plasmids?",
  options: [
    "(A) Extra-chromosomal",
    "(B) Self-replicating",
    "(C) Circular",
    "(D) Single stranded"
  ],
  answer: "(D) Single stranded"
},

{
  question: "The 'molecular scissors' fall in the category of:",
  options: [
    "(A) Exonuclease",
    "(B) Endonuclease",
    "(C) Restriction enzymes",
    "(D) Cleaving enzyme"
  ],
  answer: "(C) Restriction enzymes"
},

{
  question: "Match the enzymes with their functions:\nP. DNA Ligase\nQ. Restriction exonuclease\nR. Taq polymerase\nS. Restriction endonuclease",
  options: [
    "(A) P-i, Q-iv, R-iii, S-ii",
    "(B) P-iii, Q-i, R-ii, S-iv",
    "(C) P-i, Q-ii, R-iv, S-iii",
    "(D) P-iv, Q-iii, R-ii, S-i"
  ],
  answer: "(B) P-iii, Q-i, R-ii, S-iv"
},

{
  question: "The organism used in construction of the first artificial recombinant DNA by Cohen and Boyer in 1972 was:",
  options: [
    "(A) Agrobacterium tumefaciens",
    "(B) Bacillus thuringiensis",
    "(C) Salmonella typhimurium",
    "(D) E. coli"
  ],
  answer: "(D) E. coli"
},

{
  question: "Introduction of an alien DNA into a plant host cell is achieved by making them:",
  options: [
    "(A) Using gene gun",
    "(B) Competent with bivalent ions",
    "(C) Using lysozymes and chitinase",
    "(D) Using microinjections"
  ],
  answer: "(A) Using gene gun"
},

{
  question: "What is the cell that receives a recombinant gene called?",
  answer: "Transgenic cell"
},

{
  question: "Suggest a technique to a researcher who needs to separate fragments of DNA.",
  answer: "Agarose Gel Electrophoresis"
},







  /// aseration type


  {
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "A piece of DNA inserted into an alien organism generally does not replicate, if not inserted into a chromosome.",
  reason: "Chromosomes have specific sequences called 'ori' region, where DNA replication is initiated.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) A true R false",
    "(C) A false R true",
    "(D) Both true but incorrect explanation",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "A bioreactor provides the optimal conditions for achieving the desired product by providing optimum growth conditions.",
  reason: "The most commonly used bioreactors are of stirring type.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "Restriction endonuclease recognises palindromic sequence in DNA and cuts them.",
  reason: "Palindromic sequence has two unique recognition sites PstI and PvuI recognised by restriction endonuclease.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "The stirrer facilitates the even mixing of oxygen availability in a bioreactor.",
  reason: "Stirred-tank bioreactors generally have a flat base.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "Specific enzymes are used to degrade the cell wall in organisms to isolate the DNA from the cell.",
  reason: "Fungal cell wall is degraded by the enzyme cellulase.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "Plasmids are autonomously replicating circular extrachromosomal DNA.",
  reason: "Plasmids are usually present in Eukaryotic cells.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "Synthetic oligonucleotide polymers are used during Annealing in a PCR.",
  reason: "The primers bind to the double stranded DNA at their complementary regions.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},



  ]
};
